# Dr. Domenico Giusti

#### CONTACTS:

Senckenberg Centre for Human Evolution and Palaeoenvironment & Eberhard Karls Universität Tübingen - AG: Paläoanthropologie

Rümelinstr. 23, 72070 Tübingen, Germania

**1** +49 (0) 1733835433

□ +39 3936476718

3 dncgst



Dr. Giusti's main research interest lies in the study of archaeological site formation processes through spatial analysis. He is specialized in computer applications and quantitative methods in archaeological research. Since 2009 he is active in international archaeological research projects.

Main research interests: ●Palaeolithic archaeology ●Site formation processes ●Taphonomy ●Spatial analysis

# Current position

### Research-Technician, since 2017

Senckenberg Centre for Human Evolution and Palaeoenvironment (SHEP) & Eberhard Karls Universität Tübingen - AG: Paläoanthropologie

Activities: GIS-based documentation of archaeological excavations and surveys, image-based modeling, database management, exploratory and hypothesis-driven spatial data analysis.

### Academic background

## **₱ PhD**, 2014–2018

Doctor of Science (Dr. rer. nat.) in Archaeological Science

Eberhard Karls Universität Tübingen

Thesis: "Application of spatial statistics to the study of site formation processes"

(grade: magna cum laude)

## **ሾ** MSc, 2010−2012

International Master in Quaternary and Prehistory

University of Ferrara, Italy

Thesis: "Application of spatial technologies to the Paleolithic site of Pirro Nord (Apricena), Italy"

(grade: 30/30)

## MA (pre Bologna process), 1998–2006

Master in Cultural Heritage Management

University of Perugia, Italy

Thesis: "The ethnographic museums in the provence of Teramo, Italy: A museographic survey"

(grade: 102/110)

# Other education and training

#### MOOCs

Reproducible Research, 2021

Offered by: Johns Hopkins University through Coursera

 $\Re$  R Programming, 2021

Offered by: Johns Hopkins University through Coursera

Representation of the Pata Scientist's Toolbox, 2021

Offered by: Johns Hopkins University through Coursera

& Machine Learning, 2020

Offered by: Stanford University through Coursera

AI For Everyone, 2020

Offered by: deeplearning.ai through Coursera

#### Professional Course

& GIS (Geographic Information System) with Free Software, 2012 Offered by: CTS Bozen, University of Bozen, TrueLite, Faunalia

#### Short courses

**♦** *QGIS/GRASS*, 2011

Offered by: Faunalia

Reprinciples and Applications of Global Positioning System (GPS), 2011

Offered by: CGT, University of Siena

**♣** DataBase, 2011

Offered by: CGT, University of Siena

# Teaching activities

**a** Adjunct Lecturer at the Eberhard Karls Universität Tübingen, 2021

Class: 'Open Science. Basic principles and best practices'

## Fieldwork experience

# ARCHAEOLOGICAL EXCAVATIONS

- ♥ Sala del Fuoco, Grotta del Fiume, 2021, Frasassi, Italy [Scientific and field director]
- f TSR, 2015–2021, Macedonia, Greece
- **♥** Marathousa 1, 2014–2019, Megalopolis, Greece
- **♀** *Dibbe Rockshelter*, 2018, Oromiya, Ethiopia
- **♥** Morfi, 2017, Epirus, Greece
- ♥ Pirro Nord, 2010–2015, Apricena, Italy
- ♥ Gradiscje di Codroipo, 2009, Codroipo, Italy

#### Archaeological surveys

- **♥** Megalopolis Basin, 2018–2021, Peloponnese, Greece
- **♀** Awash-Megenta, 2018, Afar, Ethiopia
- **♥** *Middle Kalamas*, 2015–2016, Epirus, Greece
- **♦** Mygdonia Basin, 2014, Macedonia, Greece

# Professional experience

# RESCUE ARCHAEOLOGY

- archeoRes, 2013, Cremona, Italy
- **◊** Arc-Team, 2013, Laives/Leifers, Italy
- **♦** Archeologia e Restauro, 2013, Bologna, Italy
- **◊** Archeologia e Restauro, 2010–2012, Bologna, Italy
- **♀** AR/S Archeosistemi, 2009, Vicenza, Italy

#### Museums

- m Comune di Ferrara, Centro di Documentazione storica, 2007–2008, Italy
- m Museo Civico Archeologico di Teramo, 2007, Italy
- museo Etnografico Teramano, 2006–2007, Italy

#### Public Sector

Regione Abruzzo, 2006, Italy

### Memberships

European Society for the Study of Human Evolution (ESHE); Computer Applications and Quantitative Methods in Archaeology (CAA)

# Reviewer for journals

Journal of Archaeological Science, Journal of Archaeological Science: Reports, Journal of Human Evolution, Archaeological and Anthropological Sciences

### **Publications**

#### PEER-REVIEWED JOURNAL ARTICLES

Starkovich B. M., Cuthbertson P., Kitagawa K., Thompson N., Konidaris G. E., Rots V, Münzel S. C., Giusti D., Schmid V. C., Blanco-Lapaz A., Lepers C., Tourloukis V. 2021. Minimal Tools, Maximum Meat: A Pilot Experiment to Butcher an Elephant Foot and Make Elephant Bone Tools Using Lower Paleolithic Stone Tool Technology. *Ethnoarchaeology*. DOI: 10.1080/19442890.2020.1864877.



#### Chapters in edited volumes

Giusti D. 2021. Investigating the spatio-temporal dimension of past human-elephant interactions: A spatial taphonomic approach. In: *Human-Elephant Interactions. From Past to Present*. Ed. by

- Harvati K., Barkai R., Konidaris G., Tourloukis V. Tuebingen.
- Menéndez L. P., Giusti D. 2018. Global and local trends of craniofacial variation in southern South America. In: New Perspectives on the Peopling of the Americas. Ed. by Harvati K., Jaeger G. and Reyes-Centeno H. Tuebingen: Kerns Verlag.

#### Published conference abstracts

- □ Giusti D. 2019. Investigating the spatio-temporal dimension of human-elephant interactions: a spatial taphonomic approach. VWS Symposium Human-elephant interactions: from past to present, 16–18 October 2019, Hannover, Germany.
- □ Konidaris G. E., Tourloukis V., Athanassiou A., Giusti D., Thompson N., Panagopoulou E., Karkanas P., Harvati K. 2019. Marathousa 2: A new Middle Pleistocene locality in Megalopolis Basin (Greece) with evidence of human modifications on faunal remains. In: Proceedings of the European Society for the Study of Human Evolution 9, 82. Liège.
- □ Tourloukis V., Konidaris G. E., **Giusti D.**, Karkanas P., Thompson N., Athanassiou A., Tsartsidou G., Panagopoulou E., Harvati K. 20018. Small tools, big bones: first results from the Lower Palaeolithic site of Marathousa 1, Megalopolis, Greece. XVIII world UISPP Congress. Paris
- □ Giusti D., Tourloukis V., Konidaris G. E., Thompson N., Karkanas P., Panagopoulou E., Harvati K. 2017. Beyond maps: Patterns of formation processes at the Middle Pleistocene open-air site of Marathousa 1, Megalopolis Basin, Greece. In: Proceedings of the European Society for the Study of Human Evolution 6, 74. Leiden.
- □ Harvati K., Panagopoulou E., Tourloukis V., Thompson N., Karkanas P., Konidaris G. E., Athanassiou A., Tsartsidou G., Giusti D. 2017. Marathousa 1: New Lower Paleolithic elephant butchering site from the Megalopolis basin, Greece. In: Proceedings of the European Society for the Study of Human Evolution 6, 84. Leiden.
- □ Konidaris G. E., Athanassiou A., Tourloukis, V., Thompson N., Giusti D., Panagopoulou E., Harvati K. 2017. The Elephas (Palaeoloxodon) antiquus skeleton and other large mammals from the Lower Palaeolithic locality Marathousa 1 (Megalopolis Basin, Greece): preliminary results. In: Proceedings of the European Society for the Study of Human Evolution 6, 104. Leiden.
- □ Tourloukis V., Thompson N., Panagopoulou E., Konidaris G. E., **Giusti D.**, Athanassiou A., Tsartsidou G., Karkanas P., Harvati K. 2017. The lithic assemblage and bone tools from the Lower Palaeolithic site of Marathousa 1, Megalopolis, Greece: first results. In: *Proceedings of the European Society for the Study of Human Evolution* 6, 202. Leiden.
- □ Harvati K., Panagopoulou E., Tourloukis V., Thompson N., Karkanas P., Athanassiou A., Konidaris G. E., Tsartsidou G., Giusti D. 2016. New Middle Pleistocene elephant butchering site from Greece.
  In: Abstracts of the Paleoanthropology Society 2016 Meeting. PaleoAnthropology, A14-A15.
- □ Giusti D. 2016. Applicazioni FLOSS per l'acquisizione, gestione ed analisi dei dati archeologici. Il caso studio del sito paleolitico di Pirro Nord, Apricena (FG), Italia. In: ArcheoFOSS Free, Libre and Open Source Software e Open Format nei processi di ricerca archeologica. Atti del VIII Workshop (Catania, 2013). Ed. by F. Stanco and G. Gallo G. Archaeopress.
- □ Giusti D. 2013. A GIS approach to the Paleolithic site of Pirro Nord, Italy: From data management to spatial analysis through a Wiki documentation. In: Proceedings of the European Society for the Study of Human Evolution 2, 98. Vienna.

#### Archaeological Reports (non-refereed)

Panagopoulou E., Tourloukis V., Thompson N., Athanassiou A., Konidaris G., Tsartsidou G., **Giusti D.**, Harvati K. [in press] Excavations at the Marathousa 1 site, Megalopolis, Arcadia: research campaign 2017. Archaeologiko Deltio, Chronika 2017 (in Greek).

- Panagopoulou E., Tourloukis V., Thompson N., Athanassiou A., Konidaris G., Tsartsidou G., **Giusti D.**, Harvati K. [in press] Excavations at the Marathousa 1 site, Megalopolis, Arcadia: research campaign 2016. Archaeologiko Deltio, Chronika 2016 (in Greek).
- Panagopoulou E., Harvati K., Tourloukis V., Thompson N., Athanassiou A., Karkanas P., Tsartsidou G., Konidaris G., **Giusti D**. 2020. Systematic excavation at Marathousa 1, Megalopolis, Arcadia: 2014 research campaign. Archaeologiko Deltio, Chronika 2014 (in Greek).

Tübingen, November 25, 2021

Dowell